A Guide to the Papers of Ralph Eisenberg, 1950-1973
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Ralph Eisenberg 1950-1973
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12774
This collection consists of ca. 9,500 items (19 Hollinger boxes; 8 linear shelf feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the Library on November 30, 1983, and was made a gift to the Library by Mrs. Ralph Eisenberg of Charlottesville, Virginia, on March 6, 1984.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Ralph Eisenberg consist of ca. 9,500 items (19 Hollinger boxes; 8 linear shelf feet), 1950-1973, chiefly pertaining to his career as a professor of government at the University of Virginia. The collection contains correspondence, research notes, manuscripts, articles, reviews, lectures, newsclippings, minutes, and reports. The major portion of the collection concerns Eisenberg's work as a consultant and speaker, research for his book, Virginia Votes, 1924-1968, departmental activities and participation on various University committees.
Eisenberg's teaching career is documented by the exams and quizzes, syllabi, lectures, notes, course files, student papers, student thesis proposals, and letters of recommendation present in the collection. His activities as a political analyst and consultant include work with the Charlottesville-Albemarle County Merger Committee, the American Broadcasting Company Radio and Television Network, WTAR and WTAR-TV (Norfolk, Va.), the Virginia Commission on Redistricting, the Seminar for Southern Journalists of the Southern Newspaper Publishers' Association Foundation, Henrico County Redistricting litigation, and the Virginia Constitutional Revision Commission.
Correspondents include: W.W. Abbot, William C. Battle, Staige Blackford, Joel T. Broyhill, Albert V. Bryan, Robert Y. Button, John Warren Cooke, Weldon Cooper, Wayne Dumont, Jr., George Dyer, Benjamin Franklin III, John B. Fuller, Ray L. Garland, Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Richard W. Griffin, Burr P. Harrison, William C. Havard, Frank L. Hereford, Jr., Henry E. Howell, Jr., Victor T. LeVine, C. Harrison Mann, Jr., John O. Marsh, Jr., J. Harry Michael, Jr., William V. Musto, C. Armonde Paxson, Albert H. Quie, J. Sargeant Reynolds, Vincent L. Sexton, Jr., William B. Spong, Jr., Rocco J. Tresolini, and Murat Williams.
The collection contains very little material relating to Eisenberg's work as an assistant and associate director of the Institute of Government at the University of Virginia and as assistant provost of the University.
Organization
The original order of the papers has been retained whenever possible, with a few modifications. The papers are organized into the following ten series: I: Correspondence, in three sections, general, topical, and personal; II: Personal Papers; III: Professional Papers; IV: U.Va. Government and Foreign Affairs Department; V: U.Va Committees, all arranged alphabetically by committee name or topic; VI: Manuscripts and Related Materials, arranged alphabetically by title; VII: Research Files, in three sections: Virginia Votes chronological file, Virginia Votes general file, and miscellaneous research; VIII: Miscellaneous Articles, arranged alphabetically by author; IX: Letters of Recommendation, and X: Oversize Item.
Contents List
- Series I, Correspondence
  - Subseries A: General
    - Correspondence-General 1961-1969, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence-General 1970-1973; n.d., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Subseries B: Topical
    - B'nai B'rith 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Devaluation of the Urban and Suburban Vote 1961-1964; 1966, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Emphasis Magazine Column 1968 (Box 2)
    - Grants 1961; 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Havard's Book on Southern Politics 1966-1972 (Box 2)
    - Henry E. Howell, Jr. 1963 and 1973 (Box 2)
    - National Capital Area Center for Education in Politics 1964-1966, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - National Center for Education in Politics 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    - National Government Casebook 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - National Municipal League 1965-1968; 1971 (Box 3)
    - Prentice-Hall, Inc. 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - Virginia Chapter in The New Southern Politics1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Subseries C: Personal
    - Correspondence-Personal 1958-1961; 1963-1966, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Correspondence-Personal 1967-1973, 4 folders (Box 4)
- Series II: Personal Papers
  - A Comparative View of Political Parties in Mexico and Chile - R.E. Class Paper 1956, TMs. (Box 4)
  - Charlottesville Council of Parent Teacher Associations 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Local Legislation and the Legislative Process in New Jersey - Dissertation at Princeton University 1960, TMs. (Box 4)
  - 1952 Presidential Election in Mexico - Thesis at the University of Illinois 1953, TMs. (Box 4)
  - R.E. Appointment Book 1972 (Box 4)
  - R.E. Class Notes - University of Illinois 1950-1952 (Box 5)
  - R.E. Graduate Exams - Princeton University 1957 (Box 5)
  - Strategic Factors in the Setting of Mexican Foreign Policy - R. E. Class Paper 1956, TMs. (Box 5)
  - Vitae n.d. (Box 5)
- Series III: Professional Papers
  - American Broadcasting Company Elections Consultant 1964-1968 (Box 5)
  - American Broadcasting Company Elections '66 Fact Book 1966, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Arlington Committee of 100 Meeting 1971 (Box 6)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle County Merger Committee n.d. (Box 6)
  - Democratic State Convention 1968 (Box 6)
  - Henrico County Redistricting Materials [1968] (Box 6)
  - Management Development Program 1973 (Box 6)
  - National Municipal League National Conference on Government 1971 (Box 6)
  - New Jersey Institutions and Agencies Commission 1958-1959 (Box 6)
  - Republican State Convention 1970-1971 (Box 6)
  - Reserve Officers Training Corps Program 1973 (Box 6)
  - Selection of National Party Convention Delegates 1968 (Box 6)
  - Seminar for Southern Journalists of the Southern Newspaper Publishers' Association 1968 and 1971 September (Box 6)
  - Seminar for Southern Journalists of the Southern Newspaper Publishers' Association 1971 Oct-Dec (Box 7)
  - Seminars in Executive Development, Front Royal, Virginia 1971 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Constitutional Revision Commission 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Virginia Legislature Study [1966] (Box 7)
  - Virginia Redistricting Plan 1961-1966, 1968-1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - WTAR Radio-TV Corporation, Norfolk, Va. 1965-1966 (Box 7)
- Series IV: U.Va. Government and Foreign Affairs Dept.
  - Austin, Jack - Dissertation 1973 (Box 8)
  - Goldberg, Joseph E. - Vita n.d. (Box 8)
  - Government and Foreign Affairs Dept. - Curriculum Regulations 1970-1972 (Box 8)
  - Government and Foreign Affairs Dept. - Memoranda and Minutes 1969-1973 (Box 8)
  - Government and Foreign Affairs Departmental Graduate Committee 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Municipal Law n.d. (Box 8)
  - Municipal Law-Used Lectures n.d. (Box 8)
  - The National Government of the United States 1960-1961 (Box 8)
  - State and Local Government 1967-1973, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - State and Local Government - Lecture Materials 1970-1972 (Box 9)
  - State and Local Government - Notes n.d.; 1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - State and Local Government - Old Records 1966-1971 (Box 9)
  - State and Local Government - Quizzes 1967-1973 (Box 9)
  - Student Exams 1971 (Box 9)
  - Student Papers: B-D 1963; 1971; 1973; n.d. (Box 9)
  - Student Papers: E-L 1971 and 1973 (Box 9)
  - Student Papers: M-S 1970; n.d. (Box 10)
  - Student Papers: W-Z 1966; 1971; 1973 (Box 10)
  - Student Thesis Proposals 1965-1972, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Virginia Government and Politics 1969-1971 (Box 10)
- Series V: University of Virginia Committees
  - Committee on Academic Legislation - Report 1970 (Box 10)
  - Committee on Bylaws 1970 (Box 10)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Public Affairs (Mosher Committee) 1972 (Box 10)
  - Committee on Educational and Employment Opportunities, Obligations, and Rights 1969; 1970, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Committee on Educational and Employment Opportunities, Obligations, and Rights - Reports 1966-1970 (Box 11)
  - Committee on Student Financial Aid 1963-1964 (Box 11)
  - Committee on the Future of the University 1971-1972 (Box 12)
  - Committee on the Presence of the Students at Faculty Meetings 1969; 1970, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Committee on the Presence of the Students at Faculty Meetings - Faculty Letters 1969-1970 (Box 12)
  - Committee to Study the Master of Arts Program in Public Administration 1965-1967 (Box 12)
  - Faculty, Tenure and Promotions 1973 (Box 12)
  - Foreign Affairs - Political Science Department Consolidation Committee 1964 (Box 12)
  - School of Education Table of Organization Report 1972 (Box 12)
  - Status of Baccalaureate Degree Recipients of 1964-1966, 1968, and 1972 Six Months After Graduation - Office of Institutional Analysis 1973 (Box 12)
  - University Committee on Students 1969-1970 (Box 12)
- Series VI: Manuscripts and Related Materials
  - Conflict of Interests and the Public Service: Deterrents to Problem-Solving n.d., TMs. (Box 13)
  - Conflicts of Interest Among Government Officers and Employees in Great Britain 1957, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Conflicts of Interest Situations and Remedies 1959, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Devaluation of the Urban and Suburban Vote, Volume I and II 1961-1962, Printed (Box 13)
  - Highlights and Implications of State Legislative Apportionment Decisions 1962, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Local Government Representation: Districting Dilemmas and Issues 1971, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Printed 1959-1966 (Box 13)
  - The New Virginia Elects a Governor 1966, TMs. (Box 13)
  - 1957-1958 Legislation and the Legislature 1958, TMs. (Box 13)
  - 1966 Politics in Virginia: The Elections for U.S. Senator 1967, TMs. (Box 13)
  - 1969 Politics in Virginia: The General Election n.d., TMs. (Box 13)
  - 1972 Election in Virginia: Impact and Future Prospects n.d., TMs. (Box 13)
  - The 1972 Elections: Political Prognosis for Nation and State 1972, AMs (Box 13)
  - One Man-One Vote and Local Governing Bodies 1966, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Organization for Outdoor Recreation in South Carolina 1960, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Readings in Virginia Government 1965 (Box 13)
  - Reapportionment and a Legislature: Some Observations of the Virginia Experience 1967, TMs. (Box 13)
  - Reapportionment and Urban Underrepresentation in State Legislatures n.d., TMs. (Box 13)
  - Recent Developments in State Legislative Reapportionment 1962, TMs. (Box 13)
  - State Legislative Redistricting: Some Practical Issues in the Wake of Judicial Decision 1962, TMs. (Box 13)
  - The University of Virginia News Letter 1961-1971 (Box 13)
  - Virginia Chapter in The Changing Politics of the South1969, TMs. (Box 14)
  - Virginia Chapter in The Changing Politics of the South1970-1971, TMs. (Box 14)
  - Virginia Reapportions: A Journey Through a Judicial Thicket 1965, TMs. (Box 14)
  - Virginia Votes for President: Patterns and Prospects 1964, TMs. (Box 14)
  - Virginia's New Look Governor: Style and Image in the Developing South 1971, TMs. (Box 14)
- Series VII: Research Files (Box 14)
  - 1948 Democratic Senatorial Primary and Presidential General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1949 Gubernatorial General Election and Democratic Primary n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1952 Presidential and U.S. Senatorial Election and Democratic U.S. Senatorial Primary n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1953 Gubernatorial General Election and Democratic Primary n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1954 U.S. Senatorial General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1956 Presidential General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1957 Gubernatorial General Election and Democratic Primary n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1958 U.S. Senatorial General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1960 U.S. Presidential General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1961 Gubernatorial General Election n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1962 Congressional General Elections n.d. (Box 14)
  - 1964 Presidential General Election 1963-1965 (Box 14)
  - 1965 Gubernatorial General Election n.d.; 1966 (Box 14)
  - 1966 U.S. Senatorial General Election and Democratic U.S. Senatorial Primary 1966-1967 (Box 14)
  - 1968 Presidential General Election 1968 (Box 15)
  - 1969 Gubernatorial Democratic Primary 1969-1970 (Box 15)
  - 1969 Gubernatorial General Election 1969-1970; n.d., 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1970 U.S. Senatorial General Election and Democratic Primary 1970 (Box 15)
  - 1971 General and Special Elections 1971 (Box 15)
  - 1972 Presidential General Election 1972 (Box 15)
  - Virginia Votes, 1924-1968 1971, TMs. (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1924-1968 - Computer Data n.d., 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1924-1968 - Notes n.d., 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1924-1968 - Statistics n.d. (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1924-1968 - Various Drafts n.d. (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1969-1971 n.d. (Box 16)
  - Virginia Votes, 1969-1971 - Notes n.d. (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Working Papers Re Virginia Politics and Voting 1961-1973 (Box 17)
  - Federal Conflict of Interest Laws 1960; 1966; 1968 (Box 17)
  - Legislative Apportionment - Court Decisions 1961-1962 (Box 17)
  - Legislative Apportionment - Programming Data n.d. (Box 17)
  - New Detroit Committee Materials 1967-1968, TMs. (Box 17)
  - Virginia Registrar Questionnaire 1967 (Box 17)
- Series VIII: Miscellaneous Articles
  - Baker, Gordon E. - "Nursing Self-Inflicted Wounds: The Reformer's Guide Through Some Reinvigorated Thorns in the Political Thicket" 1971, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Bernd, Joseph L. - "The Peripheral South in the 1972 Presidential Election" 1973, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Bernstein, Marver H. - "A Perspective on Ethical Problems in State and Local Government" 1971, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Bowman, Lewis - "Political and Social Attitudes in Charlottesville" 1966, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Buchanan, William - "The Market for Doctoral Instruction in Political Science" 1967, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Burke, Robert L. - "Virginia's Silent Minority: A Computerized Analysis of Non-Voting in the Old Dominion" 1970, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Committee on Governmental Structure - "Metropolitan Virginia: A Program for Action" 1967, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "Elements of a Doctrine of Mid-Career University Education in Public Policy and Management for Public Officials" 1966, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "Index Numbers of Party Strength in the American Electorate: National Conventions of 1964 and 1968" 1963, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "Memorandum on Apportionment of Voting Strength in the Democratic National Conventions of 1964 and 1968" 1963, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "Presidential Candidates: Typical Careers, Past and Future" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "The Record of 1960 in Selecting the Presidential and Vice-Presidential Candidates" 1960 (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "A Revised Schedule for the Election of the Congress and the President, Convening of the Congress, and Inauguration of the President" 1965, TMs. (Box 18)
  - David, Paul T. - "The Role of the Vice-President in Urban Affairs" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Dixon, Robert G., Jr. - "Some Political Theories in Legislative Reapportionment Decisions - The Eschatology of 'One Man-One Vote'" 1965, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Emmerich, Herbert - "Public Administration in Perspective: Problems, Trends, and Prospects" 1966, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Frisch, Morton J. - "The Place of Theory in American Political Life" [1963], TMs. (Box 18)
  - Frisch, Morton J. - "Roosevelt on Peace and Freedom" n.d. (Box 18)
  - Henry, Laurin L. - "The Presidency, Executive Staffing, and the Federal Bureaucracy" 1967, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Hoagland, Alexander C., Jr. - "Conflict of Interest - A Lawyer's Point of View" n.d., TMs. (Box 18)
  - Jackson, Edward R. and Prestage, Jewel L. "Political Science in the Black Colleges" 1969, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Jewell, Malcolm E. - "Effects of Redistricting on Metropolitan Legislative Behavior" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Jewell, Malcolm E. - "The Place Method in State Legislative Elections" 1966 (Box 18)
  - Kirby, Jack Temple - "The Democratic Organization and its Challenges, 1899-1922" 1965, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Kolodziej, Edward A. - "Rational Consent and Defense Budgets: The Role of Congress, 1945-1962" 1963, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Kolodziej, Edward A. - "Vietnam: Gresham's Law and Military Strategy" n.d., TMs. (Box 18)
  - Kolodziej, Edward A. - "When Strangers Meet: Congress and Foreign Policy Debate" 1966, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Leuthold, David A. - "The Effects of Legislative Reapportionment on Policy: Michigan and Missouri" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Mathewson, Kent - "The Message ... Suburbia ... Is Dignity" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Mauer, George - "Evolving Issues and Patterns of State Legislative Redistricting in the Oklahoma City Metropolitan Area" 1965, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Norris, Donald F. - "Partisan Elections in Virginia's Cities" 1967, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Smith, Hampden H., III - Changes from Primaries to Conventions in the Virginia Democratic Party" n.d., TMs. (Box 18)
  - Thornton, Neal - "Virginia Politics" 1958, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Verney, Douglas - "Political Patterns Within North America: A Transatlantic View of Virginia and Quebec, Florida and Ontario" 1968, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Weir, Charles W. - "The Lieutenant Governor's Race in Virginia - 1971" n.d., TMs. (Box 18)
  - Wheeler, John P., Jr. - "The States in the 'New Federalism" 1966, TMs. (Box 18)
  - "The Civil Service - Hatch Act Record of Lyndon B. Johnson" 1964, TMs. (Box 18)
  - Rules of the General Assembly 1958, TMs. (Box 18)
- Series IX: Letters of Recommendation
  - Recommendations - Graduate Students 1964-1971 (Box 19)
  - Recommendations - Undergraduate Students 1961-1971 (Box 19)
    Restricted
- Series X: Oversize Items
  - "The Unfinished Portrait" by Elizabeth Shoumatoff. Color print of the unfinished portrait of Franklin Delano Roosevelt. n.d., Print
  - Martin, Harold - "The Unfinished Portrait" (History of the above painting) n.d., Printed